<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<prayer name="Matins;Morning Prayer;Lauds" rite="i">

<!--
    Note that the XML-ification of this document
    is a work in progress; this is not yet fit
    for machine consumption.
  -->

<section name="Opening Sentence"> 
<one-of>
<reading from="Mark 13:35, 36" if="advent"> 
Watch ye , for ye know not when the master of the house
cometh, at even, or at midnight, or at the cock-crowing, or in
the morning; lest coming suddenly he find you sleeping.
</reading>
<reading from="Isaiah 40:3" if="advent">
Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make straight in the desert a
highway for our God.
</reading>
<reading from="Isaiah 40:5" if="advent">
The glory of the Lord shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see
it together.
</reading>
<reading from="Luke 2:10, 11" if="christmas">
Behold, I bring you good tidings of a great joy, which shall be
to all people.  For unto you is born this day in the city of
David a Savior, which is Christ the Lord.
</reading>
<reading from="Revelation 21:3" if="christmas">
Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell
with them, and they shall be his people, and God himself
shall be with them, and be their God.
</reading>
<reading from="Isaiah 60:3" if="epiphany">
The Gentiles shall come to thy light, and kings to the bright-
ness of thy rising.
</reading>
<reading from="Isaiah 49:6b" if="epiphany">
I will give thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayest be
my salvation unto the end of the earth.
</reading>
<reading from="Malachi 1:11" if="epiphany"> 
From the rising of the sun even unto the going down of the
same my Name shall be great among the Gentiles, and in
every place incense shall be offered unto my Name, and a
pure offering: for my Name shall be great among the heathen,
saith the Lord of hosts.
</reading>
<reading from="1 John 1:8, 9" if="lent">
If we say we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the
truth is not in us, but if we confess our sins, God is faithful
and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all
unrighteousness.
</reading>
<!-- TO HERE -->
<reading from="Joel 2:13" if="lent">
Rend your heart, and not your garments, and turn unto the
Lord your God; for he is gracious and merciful, slow to
anger and of great kindness, and repenteth him of evil.
</reading>
<reading if="lent">
 
I will arise and go to my father, and will say unto him,
"Father, I have sinned against heaven, and before thee; and
am no more worthy to be called thy son."  =Luke 15:18, 19=
</reading>
<reading if="lent">
 
To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgivenesses,
though we have rebelled against him; neither have we obeyed
the voice of the Lord our God, to walk in his laws which he
set before us.  =Daniel 9:9, 10=
</reading>
<reading from="Mark 8:34" if="lent">
Jesus said, &quot;Whosoever will come after me, let him deny
himself, and take up his cross, and follow me.&quot;
</reading>
<reading if="holyweek">
All we like sheep have gone astray; we have turned every one
to his own way; and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of
us all.  =Isaiah 53:6=
 
Is it nothing to you, all ye that pass by?  Behold and see if
there be any sorrow like unto my sorrow which is done unto
me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me.  =Lamentations 1:12=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
 
=Easter Season, including Ascension Day and the Day of
Pentecost=
 
Alleluia! Christ is risen.
=The Lord is risen indeed. Alleluia!=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
This is the day which the Lord hath made; we will rejoice and
be glad in it.  =Psalm 118:24=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
Thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our
Lord Jesus Christ.  =1 Corinthians 15:57=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
If ye then be risen with Christ, seek the things which are
above, where Christ sitteth on the right hand of God.
=Colossians 3:1=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
Christ is not entered into a the holy places made with hands,
which are the figures of the true; but into heaven itself, now
to appear in the presence of God for us.  =Hebrews 9:24=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
Ye shall receive power after the Holy Ghost is come
upon you; and ye shall be witness unto me both in
Jerusalem, and in all Judaea, and in Samaria, and unto the
uttermost part of the earth.  =Acts 1:8=
</reading>
<reading if=""> 
=Trinity Sunday=
 
Holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and
is to come.  =Revelation 4:8=
</reading>
<reading if=""> 
=All Saints and other Major Saints' Days=
 
We give thanks unto the Father, which hath made us meet to
be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light.
=Colossians 1:12=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
Ye are no more strangers and foreigners, but fellow-citizens
with the saints and of the household of God.  =Ephesians 2:19=
</reading>
<reading if="">
 
Their sound is gone out into all lands, and their words into
the ends of the world.  =Psalm 19:4=
 <!--
 
=Occasions of Thanksgiving=
 
O give thanks unto the Lord, and call upon his Name; tell the
people what things he hath done.  =Psalm 105:1=
--> </reading>
<reading if="otherwise">
Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and
from the Lord Jesus Christ.  =Phillipians 1:2=
</reading>
<reading if="">
I was glad when they said unto me, "We will go into the
house of the Lord."  =Psalm 122:1=
</reading>
<reading if="">
Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart,
be alway acceptable in thy sight, O Lord, my strength and
my redeemer.  =Psalm 19:14=
</reading>
<reading if="">
O send out thy light and thy truth, that they may lead me,
and bring me unto thy holy hill, and to thy dwelling.
=Psalm 43:3=
</reading>
<reading if="">
The Lord is in his holy temple; let all the earth keep silence
before him.  =Habakkuk 2:20=
</reading>
<reading if="">
The hour is cometh, and now is, when the true worshipers
shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth, for the Father
seeketh such to worship him.  =John 4:23=
</reading>
<reading if="">
Thus saith the high and lofty One who inhabiteth eternity,
whose name is Holy, "I dwell in the high and holy place, with
him also that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the
spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite
ones."  =Isaiah 57:15=
</reading>
</one-of>
</section>

<section name="Confession of Sin">
 
*The Officiant says to the people*
 
Dearly beloved, we have come together in the presence of
Almighty God our heavenly Father, to render thanks for the
great benefits that we have received at his hands, to set forth
his most worthy praise, to hear this holy Word, and to ask, for
ourselves and on behalf of others, those things that are
necessary for our life and our salvation.  And so that we may
prepare ourselves in heart and mind to worship him, let us
kneel in silence, and with penitent and obedient hearts
confess our sins, that we may obtain forgiveness by his
infinite goodness and mercy.
 
*or this*
 
Let us humbly confess our sins unto Almighty God.
 
*Silence may be kept.*
 
*Officiant and People together, all kneeling*
 
Almighty and most merciful Father,
we have erred and strayed from thy ways like lost sheep,
we have followed too much the devices and desires of our own hearts,
we have offended against thy holy laws,
we have left undone those things which we ought to have done,
and we have done those things which we ought not tohave done.
But thou, O Lord, have mercy upon us,
spare thou those who confess their faults,
restore thou those who are penitent,
according to thy promises declared unto mankind
in Christ Jesus our Lord;
and grant, O most merciful Father, for his sake,
that we may hereafter live a godly, righteous, and sober life,
to the glory of thy holy Name.  Amen.
 
 
*The Priest alone stands and says*
 
The Almighty and merciful Lord grant you absolution and
remission of all your sins, true repentance, amendment of
life, and the grace and consolation of his Holy Spirit.  <amen/>
 
*A deacon or lay person using the preceding form remains kneeling, and
substitutes "us" for "you" and "our" for "your."
</section> 
 
<section name="The Invitatory and Psalter">
 
*All stand*
 
*Officiant* O Lord, open thou our lips.
*People*  And our mouth shall show forth thy praise.
 
 
*Officiant and People*
 
Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit: as
it was in the beginning, is now, and will be for ever.  Amen.
<alleluia if="not lent"/> 
 
*Then follows one of the Invitatory Psalms, Venite or Jubilate.*
</section>
 
<section name="Antiphon">
 
*In Advent*
 
Our King and Savior now draweth nigh:  O come, let us adore him.
 
 
*On the Twelve Days of Christmas*
 
Alleluia.  Unto us a child is born:  O come, let us adore him.
Alleluia.
 
 
*From the Epiphany through the Baptism of Christ, and on the Feasts of
the Transfiguration and Holy Cross*
 
The Lord hath manifested forth his glory:  O come, let us
adore him.
 
 
*In Lent*
 
The Lord is full of compassion and mercy:  O come, let us
adore him.
 
 
*From Easter Day until the Ascension*
 
Alleluia.  The Lord is risen indeed:  O come, let us adore him.
Alleluia.
 
 
*From Ascension Day until the Day of Pentecost*
 
Alleluia.  Christ the Lord ascendedeth into heaven:  O come,
 let us adore him. Alleluia.
 
 
*On the Day of Pentecost*
 
Alleluia.  The Spirit of the Lord filleth the world:  O come,
let us adore him.  Alleluia.
 
 
*On Trinity Sunday*
 
Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, one God:  O come, let us
adore him.
 
*On other Sundays and weekdays*
 
The earth is the Lord's for he made it:  O come, let us
adore him.
 
*or this*
 
Worship the Lord in the beauty of his holiness:  O come, let us
adore him.
 
*or this*
 
The mercy of the Lord is everlasting:  O come, let us adore him.
 
 
*The Alleluias in the following Antiphons are used only in Easter
Season.*
 
 
*On Feasts of the Incarnation*
 
<alleluia if="easter"/> The Word was made flesh and dwelt among us:  O come, let us
adore him. <alleluia if="easter"/>
 
*On all Saints and other Major Saints' Days*
 
<alleluia if="easter"/>  The Lord is glorious in his saints:  O come, let us
adore him.  <alleluia if="easter"/>
 
</section>

<section name="Venite"> 
=Psalm 95:1-7=
 
O come, let us sing unto the Lord; *
 let us heartily rejoice in the strength of our salvation.
 
Let us come before his presence with thanksgiving *
 and show ourselves glad in him with psalms.
 
 
For the Lord is a great God, *
 and a great King above all gods.
 
In his hand are the corners of the earth, *
 and the strength of the hills is his also.
 
The sea is his, and he made it, *
 and his hands prepared the dry land.

O come, let us worship and fall down, *
 and kneel before the Lord our Maker.
 
For he is the Lord our God, *
 and we are the people of his pasture
 and the sheep of his hand.
 
 
O worship the Lord in the beauty of holiness; *
 let the whole earth stand in awe of him.
 
For he cometh, for he cometh to judge the world
 and with righteousness to judge the world
 and the peoples with his truth.
 
*or Psalm 95, page 146.*
</section>

 
<section name="Jubilate">  =Psalm 100=
 
Be joyful in the Lord, all ye lands; *
 serve the Lord with gladness
 and come before his presence with a song.
 
Be ye sure that the Lord he is God; *
 it is he that hath made us and we ourselves;
 we are his people and the sheep of his pasture.
 
O go your way into his gates with thanksgiving
and into his courts with praise; *
 be thankful unto him and speak good of his Name.
 
For the Lord is gracious;
his mercy is everlasting; *
 and his truth endureth from generation to generation.
</section>

<section name="Pascha nostrum" if="easter"> 
*In Easter Week, in place of an Invitatory Psalm, the following is sung
or said.  It may also be used daily until the Day of Pentecost.* 
 
=1 Corinthians 5:7-8; Romans 6:9-11; 1 Corinthians 15:20-22=
 
Alleluia.
Christ our Passover is sacrificed for us; *
 therefore let us keep the feast,
 
Not with old leaven,
neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness, *
 but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth.  Alleluia.
 
 
Christ being raised from the dead dieth no more; *
 death hath no more dominion over him.
 
For in that he died, he died unto sin once; *
 but in that he liveth, he liveth unto God.
 
Likewise reckon ye also yourselves to be dead indeed unto sin, *
 but alive unto God through Jesus Christ our Lord.  Alleluia.
 
 
Christ is risen from the dead, *
 and become the first fruits of them that slept.
 
For since by man came death, *
 by man came also the resurrection of the dead.
 
For as in Adam all die, *
 even so in Christ shall all be made alive.  Alleluia.
 
 
*Then follows*
</section>

<section name="Psalter"> 

<psalm/>
 
<all>
 Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit: *
 as it was in the beginning, is now, and will be for ever.
</all>
<amen/>
 
</section>

<section name="Lessons" lessons="1">

<!-- "A lesson from..." -->
<lesson/>
 
<one-of>
<option>
<president>The Word of the Lord.</president>
<people>Thanks be to God.</people>
</option>

<option>
<president>Here endeth the Lesson.</president>
</option>
</one-of>

</section> 

<!--
*Silence may be kept after each Reading.  One of the following
Canticles, or one of those on pages 85-95 (Canticles 8-21), is sung or
said after each Reading.  If three Lessons are used, the Lesson from the
Gospel is read after the second Canticle.*

    FIXME: Canticles go in a separate file
  -->
 
<section name="The Apostles' Creed">

<all><pre>
I believe in God, the Father almighty,
 maker of heaven and earth;
 
And in Jesus Christ his only Son our Lord;
 who was conceived by the Holy Ghost,
 born of the Virgin Mary,
 suffered under Pontius Pilate,
 was crucified, dead, and buried.
 He descended into hell.
 The third day he rose again from the dead.
 He ascended into heaven,
 and sitteth on the right hand of God the Father almighty.
 From thence he shall come to judge the quick and the dead.
 
I believe in the Holy Ghost,
 the holy catholic Church,
 the communion of saints,
 the forgiveness of sins,
 the resurrection of the body,
 and the life everlasting.  Amen.
</pre></all>
</section>

<section name="The Prayers">
 
<president>The Lord be with you.</president>
 
<people>And also with you.</people>
 
<president>Let us pray.</president>
 
<all><pre>
Our Father, who art in heaven,
 hallowed be they Name,
 thy kingdom come,
 thy will be done,
 on earth as it is in heaven.
 
Give us this day our daily bread.
And forgive us our tresspasses,
 as we forgive those
 who trespass against us.
 
And lead us not into temptation,
 but deliver us from evil.
 
For thine is the kingdom,
 and the power, and the glory,
 for ever and ever.  Amen.
</pre></all>
</section>

<section name="Suffrages">

<one-of> 
<option>
<versicle-response>
O Lord, show thy mercy upon us;
And grant us thy salvation.
Endue thy ministers with righteousness;
And make thy chosen people joyful.
Give peace, O Lord, in all the world;
For only in thee can we live in safety.
Lord, keep this nation under thy care;
And guide us in the way of justice and truth.
Let thy way be known upon earth;
Thy saving health among all nations.
Let not the needy, O Lord, be forgotten;
Nor the hope of the poor be taken away.
Create in us clean hearts, O God;
And sustain us with your Holy Spirit.
</versicle-response>
</option>
 
<option>
<versicle-response>
O Lord, save thy people and bless thine heritage;
Govern them and lift them up for ever.
Day by day we magnify thee;
And we worship thy name for ever, world without end.
Vouchsafe, O Lord, to keep us this day without sin;
O Lord, have mercy upon us, hve mercy upon us.
O Lord, let thy mercy be upon us;
As our trust is in thee.
O Lord, in thee have I trusted;
Let me never be confounded.
</versicle-response>
</option>
</one-of>

</section>

<section name="A Collect for Sundays" if="sunday">
<president>
O God, who makest us glad with the weekly remembrance of
the glorious resurrection of thy Son our Lord:  Grant us this
day such blessing through our worship of thee, that the days
to come may be spent in thy favor; through Jesus
Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section>

<section name="A Collect for Fridays" if="friday">
<president> 
Almighty God, whose most dear Son went not up to joy but
first he suffered pain, and entered not into glory before he
was crucified:  Mercifully grant that we, walking in the way
of the cross, may find it none other than the way of life and
peace; through Jesus Christ your Son our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section> 
 
<section name="A Collect for Saturdays" if="saturday">
<president> 
Almighty God, who after the creation of the world didst rest
from all thy works and sanctify a day of rest for all thy
creatures:  Grant that we, putting away all earthly anxieties,
may be duly prepared for the service of thy sanctuary, and
that our rest here upon earth may be a preparation for the
eternal rest promised to thy people in heaven; through Jesus
Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section>
 
<section name="A Collect for the Renewal of Life">
<president>
O God, the King eternal, who dividest the day from the
night and turnest the shadow of death into the morning:
Drive far from us all wrong desires, incline our hearts to keep
thy law, and guide our feet into the way of peace; that,
having done thy will with cheerfulness while it was day, we
may, when night cometh, rejoice to give thee thanks;
through Jesus Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section>
  
<section name="A Collect for Peace">
<president> 
O God, who art the author of peace and lover of concord,
in knowledge of whom standeth our eternal life, whose service
is perfect freedom:  Defend us, thy humble servants, in all
assaults of our enemies; that we, surely trusting in thy
defense, may not fear the power of any adversaries; through
the might of Jesus Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section>
 
<section name="A Collect for Grace">
<president>
O Lord, our heavenly Father, almighty and everlasting God,
who hast safely brought us to the beginning of this day:
Defend us in the same with thy mighty power; and grant that
this day we fall into no sin, neither run into any kind of
danger; but that we, being ordered by thy governance, may
do always what is righteous in thy sight; through Jesus Christ
our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section> 
 
<section name="A Collect for Guidance">
<president>
O heavenly Father, in whom we live and move and have our
being:  We humbly pray thee so to guide and govern us by thy
Holy Spirit, that in all the cares and occupations of our life
we may not forget thee, but may remember that we are ever
walking in thy sight; through Jesus Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</president>
</section>
 
<section name="A Collect for Mission">
<president>
<one-of>
<option>
Almighty and everlasting God, by whose Spirit the whole
body of thy faithful people is governed and sanctified:
Receive our supplications and prayers which we offer before
thee for all members of thy holy Church, that in their
vocation and ministry they may truly and godly serve thee;
through our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.  <amen/>
</option>

<option>
O God, who hast made of one blood all the peoples of the
earth, and didst send thy blessed Son to preach peace to those
who are far off and to those who are near:  Grant that people
everywhere may seek after thee and find thee; bring the
nations into thy fold; pour out thy Spirit upon all flesh; and
hasten the coming of thy kingdom; through the same thy
Son Jesus Christ our Lord.  <amen/>
</option>

<option>
Lord Jesus Christ, who didst stretch out thine arms of love
on the hard wood of the cross that everyone might come
within the reach of thy saving embrace:  So clothe us in thy
Spirit that we, reaching forth our hands in love, may bring
those who do not know thee to the knowledge and love of
you; for the honor of thy Name.  <amen/>
</option>

</one-of>
</president>

</section>

<section name="General Thanksgiving">
<all>
<pre>
Almighty God, Father of all mercies,
we thine unworthy servants
do give thee most humble and hearty thanks
for all thy goodness and loving-kindness
to us and to all men.
We bless thee for our creation, preservation,
and all the blessings of this life;
but above all for thine inestimable love
in the redemption of the world by our Lord Jesus Christ;
for the means of grace, and for the hope of glory.
And, we beseech thee,
give us that due sense of all thy mercies,
that our hearts may be unfaignedly thankful;
and that we show forth thy praise,
not only with our lips, but in our lives,
by giving up our selves to thy service,
and by walking before thee
in holiness and righteousness all our days;
through Jesus Christ our Lord,
to whom, with thee and the Holy Spirit,
be all honor and glory, world without end.  <amen/>
</pre>
</all>
</section>

<section name="A Prayer of St. Chrysostom">
Almighty God, who hast given us grace at this time with one
accord to make our common supplication unto thee; and
hast promised through thy well-beloved Son that when two
or three are gathered together in his Name thou wilt be in the
midst of them:  Fulfill now, O Lord, our desires and petitions
of thy servants as may be best for us; granting us in this
world knowledge of thy truth, and in the world to come life
everlasting.  <amen/>
</section>
 
<section name="Closing Sentence">
 
<president>Let us bless the Lord.</president>
<people>Thanks be to God.</people>
<alleluia if="easter"/>
<alleluia if="easter"/>

<president>
<one-of>

<reading from="2 Corinthians 13:14">
The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and
the fellowship of the Holy Ghost, be with us all evermore.
<amen/>
</reading>

<reading from="Romans 15:13">
May the God of hope fill us with all joy and peace in
believing through the power of the Holy Spirit.
<amen/>
</reading>

<reading from="Ephesians 3:20,21">
Glory to God whose power, working in us, can do infinitely
more than we can ask or imagine:  Glory to him from
generation to generation in the Church, and in Christ Jesus
for ever and ever.
<amen/>
</reading>

</one-of>
</president>
</section>
</prayer>
